So you might be asking, who's going to pay? Well, I'm going to argue that governments should fund sanitation infrastructure. NGOs and donor organizations, they can do their best, but it's not going to be enough. Governments should fund sanitation the same way they fund roads and schools and hospitals and other infrastructure like bridges, because we know, and the WHO has done this study, that for every dollar that we invest in sanitation infrastructure, we get something like three to 34 dollars back. Let's go back to the problem of pit emptying. So at North Carolina State University, we challenged our students to come up with a simple solution, and this is what they came up with: a simple, modified screw auger that can move the waste up from the pit and into a collecting drum, and now the pit worker doesn't have to go down into the pit. We tested it in South Africa, and it works. We need to make it more robust, and we're going to do more testing in Malawi and South Africa this coming year. And our idea is to make this a professionalized pit-emptying service so that we can create a small business out of it, create profits and jobs, and the hope is that, as we are rethinking sanitation, we are extending the life of these pits so that we don't have to resort to quick solutions that don't really make sense. I believe that access to adequate sanitation is a basic human right. We need to stop the practice of lower castes and lower-status people going down and being condemned to empty pits. It is our moral, it is our social and our environmental obligation. Thank you. (Applause)
Vous vous demandez peut-être : « Qui va payer ? » Eh bien, je soutiens que c'est aux gouvernements de financer les infrastructures sanitaires. Les ONG et les associations caritatives font de leur mieux, mais ça ne sera pas suffisant. C'est aux gouvernements d'assurer le financement des sanitaires, au même titre que les routes, les écoles, les hôpitaux, ou d'autres infrastructures, comme les ponts, parce que nous savons, et c'est l'OMS qui a mené cette étude, que pour chaque dollar investi dans les infrastructures sanitaires, nous récupérons entre 3 et 34 dollars. Revenons sur le problème de la vidange des fosses. À l'Université d’État de Caroline du Nord, nous avons mis au défi nos étudiants de trouver une solution simple, et voilà ce qu'ils ont trouvé : une simple vis sans fin modifiée qui peut remonter les déchets de la fosse jusque dans un bidon collecteur, et maintenant il n'est plus nécessaire de descendre dans la fosse. On l'a testé en Afrique du Sud, et ça marche. Il faut encore consolider le système, et on va faire d'autres tests au Malawi et en Afrique du Sud l'année prochaine. Notre idée est d'en faire un service professionnel de vidange de fosse, de façon à créer ainsi une petite activité, avec des emplois et des bénéfices, et nous espérons qu'en repensant l'hygiène sanitaire, nous augmenterons la durée de vie de ces fosses, sans avoir recours à des solutions d'urgence qui n'auraient pas de sens. Je pense que l'accès à des sanitaires adaptés est un droit humain fondamental. Il faut arrêter de condamner ces personnes de caste et de statut social inférieurs à descendre dans ces fosses et à les vider. Nous en avons le devoir moral, social et environnemental. Je vous remercie. (Applaudissements)